Suppose I give you two different lists of numbers
假设有两个不同的数组
or maybe two different functions
或两个不同的函数
and I ask you to think of all the ways
让你想出各种运算方式
you might combine those two lists to get a new list of numbers
来把两个数组组合在一起  得到新数组
or combine the two functions to get a new function.
或者把两个函数组合起来  得到新函数
Maybe one simple way that comes to mind
最简单的方法可能就是
is to simply add them together term by term.
一个个地把他们加起来
Likewise, with the functions, you can add all the corresponding outputs.
同样  对函数来说则是把结果对应相加
In a similar vein, you could also multiply the two lists term by term
类似的  你也可以把两个数组中的数逐个相乘
and do the same thing with the functions.
对函数也是如此
But there's another kind of combination
但有其实另一种组合方式
just as fundamental as both of those but a lot less commonly discussed
和之前提过的方式一样基础  但讨论得不多
known as a Convolution.
它被称作“卷积”
But unlike the previous two cases, it's not something that's
但和前面两种组合方式不同的是
merely inherited from an operation you can do to numbers.
它并非来源于某种数字运算
It's something genuinely new for the context of list of numbers or combining functions.
而是一种用来组合数组和函数的新方法
They show up all over the place, they are ubiquitous in image processing.
这一方法随处可见  在数字图像处理中尤为明显
It's a core construct in the theory of probability,
它是概率论中的一个核心结构
they're used a lot in solving differential equations
在求解微分方程时被大量使用
and one context where you've almost certainly seen it
而在多项式相乘的情形中  你一定见过它
if not by this name is multiplying two polynomials together.
只是可能不叫这个名字
As someone in the business of visual explanations,
对一个用可视化方式传播知识的人来说
this is an especially great topic.
这是一个非常好的选题
Because the formulaic definition in isolation and without context
因为光看没有上下文的公式化定义
can look kind of intimidating.
卷积是会有点唬人
But if we take the time to really unpack what it's saying
但是如果我告诉你卷积好处都有啥
and before that, actually motivate why you would want something like this,
再给你好好剖析下它的定义
it's an incredibly beautiful operation.
你就会发现这个运算十分美妙
And I have to admit I actually learned a little something
不得不承认  在制作这期视频的过程中
while putting together the visuals for this project.
我自己也切实地学到了一些知识
In the case of convolving two different functions,
在讲到对两个函数进行卷积的例子时
I was trying to think of different ways you might picture what that mean.
我在思考用不同的方式将其可视化
And with one of them, I had a little bit of an aha moment for
其中一个方式  让我豁然开朗
why it is that normal distributions play the role that they do in probability;
我一下子明白了  为何正态分布在概率论中如此重要
why it's such a natural shape for a function.
它的函数图像的形状为何如此自然
But I'm getting ahead of myself, there's a lot of setup for that one.
扯远了  在讲这个之前还有很多准备工作要做
In this video, our primary focus is just going to be on the discrete case
在这个视频中我们主要关注离散的卷积
and in particular building up to a very unexpected but very clever algorithm
逐步构建出一种让人拍案叫绝的计算方法
for computing these,
and I'll pull out the discussion for the continuous case into a second part.
而连续的卷积我们则放在下期视频里来讨论
翻译   saniac  清都山水郎  线头
校对   ksyx  䶭  蛋卷    时间轴   䶭    后期   鹤翔万里
It's very tempting to open up with the image processing examples
虽然用数字图像处理的例子作为开篇听起来很不错
since they're visually the most intriguing
毕竟它在可视方面是最能引起人兴趣的
but there are couple bits of finickiness
但在一些细微之处
that make the image processing case less representative of convolutions overall.
图像处理的例子不太能展现卷积的全貌
So instead, let's kick things off with probability.
所以我们还是从概率论开始吧
And in particular, one of the simplest examples
有这么一个最最简单的例子
that I'm sure everyone hears thought about at some point in their life,
相信各位观众或早或晚都曾听过
which is rolling a pair of dice
就是掷两枚骰子
and figuring out the chances of seeing various different sums.
计算两枚骰子的各个点数和的出现的概率
And you might say not a problem. Not a problem.
你可能会说  就这
Each of your two dice has six different possible outcomes,
每个骰子都有 6 种不同的结果
which gives us a total of 36 distinct possible pairs of outcomes.
总共就是六六三十六种配对可能
And if we just look through them all,
我们一个个数一遍
we can count up how many pairs have a given sum.
就可以数出每个和有多少种组合
And arranging all the pairs in a grid like this,
把所有的组合这样填在表格里
one pretty nice thing is that
有个很妙的事情是
all of the pairs that have a constant sum
相同点数和的组合
are visible along one of these different diagonals.
都排在同一条对角线上
So simply counting how many exist on each of those diagonals
所以只要数出对角线上面有多少个组合
will tell you how likely you are to see a particular sum.
就可以知道  出现某个点数和的概率是多少
And I'd say, very good, very good.
我会说：还不赖
But can you think of any other ways
但你能换一种方式展现这个问题吗
that you might visualize the same question?
Other images that can come to mind,
有没有想到其它
to think of all the distinct pairs that have a given sum?
数出某个加和的所有点数组合方式的画面
And maybe one of you raises your hand and says, 'Yeah, I've got one.'
可能有聪明的观众想说「我有想法了」
Let's say you picture these two different sets of possibilities each in a row,
把两枚骰子的所有可能结果  分别放到一行
but you flip around that second row.
然后把第二行翻转
That way, all of the different pairs which add up to seven
这样所有点数和为 7 的组合
line up vertically like this...
就会这样纵向对齐
And if we slide that bottom row all the way to the right,
如果我们把下面这行往左滑到头
then the unique pair that adds up to two, the snake eyes,
那么  加和为2的唯一一组结果
are the only ones that align.
就是唯一对齐的情况了
And if I shlunk that over one unit to the right,
如果我在往右推一个单位
the pairs which align are the two different pairs that add up to three.
就会出现两对和为 3 的组合
And in general, different offset values of this lower array,
总的来说  红色数组的不同偏移量
which remember, I had to flip around first,
（别忘了下面这行是翻转过的）
reveal all the distinct pairs that have a given sum.
对应了两个骰子的点数加和
As far as probability questions go, this still isn't especially interesting
到目前为止  这个概率问题还不算太有趣
because all we're doing is counting
因为我们只是数出了
how many outcomes there are in each of these categories.
每种点数和有多少种组合方式
But that is with the implicit assumption that
但这里面其实隐藏了一个假设
there's an equal chance for each of these faces to come up.
就是骰子的每面向上的概率是相同的
But what if I told you I have a special set of dice that's not uniform.
如果我现在改用非标的骰子
Maybe the blue die has its own set of numbers
用一个数组来描述蓝骰子每面向上的概率
describing the probabilities for each face coming up
and the red die has its own unique distinct set of numbers.
同样地  红骰子也有这样一个数组
In that case if you wanted to figure out, say, the probability of seeing a two,
这样如果你想算出和为 2 的出现概率
you would multiply the probability that the blue die is a one,
就要用蓝骰子出现 1 的概率
times the probability that the red die is a one.
乘红骰子出现 1 的概率
And for the chances of seeing a three,
如果要计算和为 3 的概率
you look at the two distinct pairs where that's possible
则需要把对应组合里
and again multiply the corresponding probabilities
点数出现的概率分别相乘
and then add those two products together.
然后再把乘积相加
Similarly, the chances of seeing a four
类似地  要计算和为 4 的情况
involves multiplying together three different pairs of possibilities
就要把三个不同组合里点数的出现概率相乘
and adding them all together.
再把他们相加
And in the spirit of setting up some formulas,
秉着要把它公式化的精神
let's name these top probabilities "a₁, a₂, a₃" and so on
我们把上面那行的概率记为 a₁ a₂ a₃...
and name the bottom ones "b₁, b₂, b₃" and so on.
把下面一行的概率记为 b₁ b₂ b₃...
And in general, this process where we are taking two different arrays of numbers,
拿出两列不同的数组、
flipping the second one around
把第二组翻转过来、
and then lining them up at various different off set values,
然后用不同偏移值把它们对齐、
taking a bunch of pairwise products and adding them up,
得到一组乘积之后再把他们加起来
that's one of the fundamental ways to think about what a convolution is.
这整个过程  便是卷积最基本的思考方式
So, just to spell it out a little more exactly-
说得更精确一些
through this process, we just generated
我们通过这个过程
probabilities for seeing two, three, four, on and on up to 12.
生成了点数和为 2 3 4 ... 12 的概率
And we got them by mixing together one list of values, A
这个过程通过某种运算将 A 和 B 数组的值交汇
and another list of values, B.
In the lingo, we'd say
说得专业一点就是
the convolution of those two sequences gives us this new sequence;
两组数的卷积生成了新的这组数
the new sequence of 11 values,
新的数列包含 11 个值
each of which looks like some sum of pairwise products.
每个值都是两数组中若干数对之积的加和
If you prefer, another way you could think about the same operation
另一种思考卷积的方式是
is to first create a table of all the pairwise products
列一个表格  计算各个组合的乘积
and then add up along all these diagonals.
然后沿着各个对角线相加
Again, that's a way of mixing together these two sequences of numbers
就把两组数混合了起来
to get us a new sequence of eleven numbers.
得到了一组 11 个数
It's the same operation as the sliding windows thought,
这个做法和滑动数列类似
just another perspective.
只是换了一种思考方式
Putting a little notation to it, here's how you might see it written down:
用上一些符号就可以写成这样
The convolution of A and B, denoted with this little asterisk, is a new list.
A 和 B 的卷积的符号是「*」 其结果是一个列表
And the nth element of that list looks like a sum
它的第 n 项定义为
and that sum goes over all different pairs of indices, i and j,
把下标 i j 之和为 n 的诸元素的乘积累加起来
so that the sum of those indices is equal to N.
It's kind of a mouthful
这可能有点啰嗦
but for example, if n was 6,
但我还是要举个例子  如果 n=6
the pairs we're going over are 1 and 5, 2 and 4, 3 and 3, 4 and 2, 5 and 1.
i 和 j 的组合 (i, j) 就是 (1, 5) (2, 4) (3, 3) (4, 2) (5, 1)
All the different pairs that add up to six.
这些组合加起来都是 6
But honestly, however you write it down, the notation is secondary
但是老实说  不管你怎么写
in importance to the visual you might hold in your head for the process.
符号在脑中留下的印象都不会太深
Here, maybe it helps to do a super simple example
这有一个超简单的例子可能会有所帮助
where I might ask you,
我要问你
what's the convolution of the list 1, 2, 3 with the list 4, 5, 6?
数组 (1, 2, 3) 和 (4, 5, 6) 的卷积是什么
You might picture taking both of these lists, flipping around that second one
你就可以想象这两个数组并排放着  翻转第二个
and then starting with its slid all the way over to the left.
然后把它（尾部）滑到最左边
Then the pair of values which align are one and four,
这时候对齐的就只有 1 和 4
multiply them together and that gives us our first term of our output.
把它们乘在一起得到输出的第一项
Slide that bottom array one unit to the right,
把第二个数组往右滑一个单位
the pairs which align are 1, 5, 2 and 4.
对齐的就会有 1 和 5、2 和 4
Multiply those pairs,
把这两对相乘
add them together and that gives us 13.
然后把乘积加在一起就得到了下一项 13
The next entry in our output.
Slide things over once more and we'll take 1×6+2×5+3×4
再滑一下  就可以得到 1×6+2×5+3×4
which happens to be 28.
算出来就是 28
One more slide and we get 2×6+3×5 and that gives us 27
再滑一下  就得到了 2×6+3×5=27
and finally the last term looks like 3×6.
最后再滑一下就是 3×6
If you'd like, you can pull up whatever your favorite programming languages
你可以用自己最喜欢的编程语言
and your favorite library that includes various numerical operations
和数值计算库跑一下
and you can confirm I'm not lying to you.
就知道我没骗你了
If you take the convolution of 1, 2, 3 against 4, 5, 6,
如果计算 (1, 2, 3) 和 (4, 5, 6) 的卷积
this is indeed the result that you'll get.
你就会得到这个结果
We've seen one case where this is a natural and desirable operation
我们已经在求和得出概率分布的例子中
adding up to probability distributions.
看到了这个运算是多么的自然和美妙
And another common example would be a moving average.
而另一个常见例子是滑动平均
Imagine you have some long list of numbers
假设有一个长数组
and you take another smaller list of numbers that all add up to one.
和另一个所有数之和为 1 的短数组
In this case, I just have a little list of five values
这里就让短数组只有五个值好了
and they're all equal to one fifth.
且每个值都等于 1/5
Then if we do this sliding window convolution process
接下来  如果我们重复这个滑动窗口卷积的过程
and kind of close our eyes and sweep under the rug what happens at the very beginning of it.
（最开始窗口出界的问题你就当没看见）
Once our smaller list of values entirely overlaps with the bigger one,
当短数组和长数组完全重叠时
think about what each term in this convolution really means.
思考下卷积的每项代表着什么
At each iteration, what you're doing is
每次迭代的时候  你实际上是
multiplying each of the values from your data by one fifth
在把数据里的每个数乘上 1/5
and adding them all together,
然后将它们加起来
which is to say
也就是说
you're taking an average of your data inside this little window.
你在求这个小窗口里数据的平均值
Overall, the process gives you a smooth out version of the original data.
总的来说  这个过程给了你一个原数据的平滑版本
And you could modify this starting with a different little list of numbers
你可以修改它  使其从一个不同的短数组开始
and as long as that little list all adds up to one,
只要短数组之和还是 1
you can still interpret it as a moving average.
你就仍可以把它解释为滑动平均
In the example shown here,
在这个例子中
that moving average would be giving more weight towards the central value.
滑动平均会给中间值更大的权重
This also results in a smooth out version of the data.
其结果也是原数据的平滑版本
If you do kind of a two dimensional analog of this,
如果你在二维上进行类似的操作
it gives you a fun algorithm for blurring a given image.
就会得到一个把图片变模糊的有趣方法
And I should say the animations I'm about to show
我应该指出  我接下来将要展示的动画
are modified from something I originally made for
是由我和 Julia Lab 在麻省理工做的
part of a set of lectures I did with the Julia Lab at MIT
一系列公开课里的内容修改而来的
for a certain open courseware class that included an image processing unit.
其中就包含了一节图像处理相关的内容
There we did a little bit more to dive into the code behind all of this.
那个视频里对图像处理背后的代码讲解得更为深入
So if you're curious, I'll leave you some links.
你感兴趣的话  可以看看评论区的链接
But focusing back on this blurring example. What's going on is
讲回到模糊图片的这个例子上  我们在做的事是
I've got this little 3×3 grid of values that marching along our original image.
用一个 3×3 的网格沿着原图像移动
And if we zoom in, each one of those values is one ninth.
放大后  每个数都是 1/9
And what I'm doing at each iteration
在每次迭代的时候
is multiplying each of those values by the corresponding pixel that it sits on top of.
将这些数值乘以它底下对应的像素值
And of course in computer science, we think of colors
当然在计算机科学中
as little vectors of three values
我们把颜色当成三维向量
representing the red, green and blue components.
三个分量分别代表红、绿、蓝
When I multiply all these little values by one ninth and I add them together,
把每个向量都乘以 1/9 然后求和
it gives us an average along each color channel
就得到了每个颜色通道的平均值
and the corresponding pixel for the image on the right is defined to be that sum.
那么右图中对应的像素就是这个加和
The overall effect as we do this for every single pixel on the image,
对每个像素都这么计算  得到的效果是
is that each one kind of bleeds into all of its neighbours
每个像素都混杂了一部分到相邻的像素中
which gives us a blurrier version than the original.
这就得到了一个比原图更模糊的版本
In the lingo, we'd say that the image on the right
用术语来说  右图就是原图和小网格的卷积
is a convolution of our original image with the little grid of values.
Or more technically, maybe I should say that
严格上讲  应该是
it's the convolution with a 180 degree rotated version of that little grid of values.
和旋转 180 度的网格的卷积
Not that it matters when the grid is symmetric
当然这在网格对称时没什么分别
but it's just worth keeping in mind that
但还是值得注意一下
the definition of a convolution, as inherited from the pure math context,
卷积的定义是从纯数学语境继承下来的
should always invite you to think about flipping around that second array.
你要牢记这个定义  把第二个数组翻转
If we modify this slightly,
如果我们稍微修改一下这个例子
we can get a much more elegant blurring effect
我们可以通过选择给网格赋予不同的数值
by choosing a different grid of values.
来得到更为美观的模糊效果
In this case, I have a little 5×5 grid,
这个例子中  有一个 5×5 网格
but the distinction is not so much its size.
但是其大小不是主要的不同
If we zoom in, we notice that the value in the middle
如果放大  我们可以看到中间的值
is a lot bigger than the value towards the edges.
比边上的值大很多
And where this is coming from, is they're all sampled from a bell curve
究其根源  这些值都从一个钟形曲线中采样得来
known as a Gaussian distribution.
这个曲线叫做高斯分布
That way, when we multiply all of these values
这样  当我们将这些数乘以
by the corresponding pixel that they're sitting on top of,
它们下面对应的像素时
we're giving a lot more weight to that central pixel
我们把更多的权重给了中间像素
and much less towards the ones out at the edge.
而只把很少的权重给了边上的像素
And just as before, the corresponding pixel on the right is defined to be this sum.
和之前一样  右图中对应的像素就是这个加和
As we do this process for every single pixel,
随着我们对每个像素都重复这个过程
it gives a blurring effect which much more authentically simulates
我们得到了一个模糊效果
the notion of putting your lens out of focus or something like that.
它更真实地模拟了镜头失焦之类的场景
But blurring is far from the only thing that you can do with this idea.
但是这个方法能做到的事情  远远不止模糊图片
For instance, take a look at this little grid of values
比如这个数值网格
which involves some positive numbers on the left
正数在左
and some negative numbers on the right,
负数在右
which I'll color with blue and red respectively.
我们来把它们分别填充为蓝色和红色
Take a moment to see if you can predict and understand
思考一下 看看你能否预测并理解
what effect this will have on the final image.
这个网格会如何影响最终图像
So in this case, I'll just be thinking of the image as grayscale instead of coloured.
这里只把图像考虑为灰度图而不是彩色图
So each of the pixels is just represented by one number instead of three.
这样每个像素就可以只用一个数来表示  而不是三个
And one thing worth noticing is that as we do this convolution,
值得一提的是  计算卷积的过程中
it's possible to get negative values.
是有可能得到负值的
For example, at this point here if we zoom in,
比如这里 放大可以看见
the left half of our little grid sits entirely on top of black pixels
网格左半边都在黑色像素上
which would have a value of zero.
所以会得到 0
But the right half of negative values all sit on top of white pixels
而网格右半边的负值都在白色像素上
which would have a value of one.
所以会得到 1
So when we multiply corresponding terms and add them together,
所以把对应项相乘再把结果相加
the result will be very negative.
会得到负数值
And the way I'm displaying this with the image on the right,
我在右图中表示这点的方法
is to color negative values red and positive values blue.
是把负数填充为红色  把正数填充为蓝色
Another thing to notice is that
另外需要注意
when you are on a patch that's all the same color, everything goes to zero
当所有小块都是同一颜色时  结果是 0
since the sum of the values in our little grid is zero.
这是因为网格中所有值相加为 0
This is very different from the previous two examples
这和之前的两个例子大为不同
where the sum of our little grid was one,
因为之前的例子里网格里数值的加和为 1
which let us interpret it as a moving average and hence a blur.
我们可以将其考虑为滑动平均  也就是模糊了图像
All in all, this little process basically detects
总而言之  这个过程是在
wherever there is variation in the pixel value as you move from left to right.
检测像素值从左到右是否有变化
And so it gives you a kind of way to pick up on all the vertical edges from your image.
所以它可以判别出图像中的所有竖向的边界
And similarly, if we rotated that grid around
用同样的逻辑  如果我们旋转这个网格
so that it varies as you move from the top to the bottom,
使得它从上到下变化
this will be picking up on all the horizontal edges.
那么它就可以判别出图像中的所有横向的边界
Which in the case of our little pi creature image,
在这个例子中  它把 π 酱的眼睛变得像个大反派
does result in some pretty demonic eyes.
This smaller grid, by the way, is often called a kernel.
顺便一提  这个小网格一般叫做“核”
And the beauty here is how just by choosing a different kernel,
巧妙之处在于  仅仅通过选择不同的核
you can get different image processing effect.
就可以产生不同的图像处理效果
Not just blurring your edge detection but also things like sharpening.
不只是模糊化边缘检测  图像的锐化也是可以的
For those of you who have heard of a convolutional neural network,
如果你听说过卷积神经网络的话
the idea there is to use data to figure out
它的思路就是用数据来算出
what the kernels should be in the first place.
应该选取什么样的核
As determined by whatever the neural network wants to detect.
这取决于想用神经网络来检测的目标
Another thing I should maybe bring up is the length of the output.
另一个应该提一嘴的事情是输出的长度
For something like the moving average example,
对滑动平均之类的情况
you might only want to think about the terms
可能只需要考虑取样窗口完全对应的情况就好了
when both of the windows fully align with each other.
Or in the image processing example,
或者在图像处理的应用中
maybe you want the final output to have the same size as the original.
可能你想要保持输出图像的尺寸和原图像相同
Now, convolutions as a pure math operation,
其实  纯数学过程上的卷积
always produce an array that's bigger than the two arrays that you started with.
产生的数组总是比两个初始数组更长
at least assuming one of them doesn't have a length of one.
至少在数组长度都大于 1 的时候是这样的
Just know that in certain computer science context,
你只需知道在某些计算机科学的背景下
you often want to deliberately truncate that output.
你需要刻意截掉一些输出值
Another thing worth highlighting is that in the computer science context,
另外值得一提的是  在计算机科学的语境下
this notion of flipping around that kernel before you let it march across the original,
将核翻转后再遍历原数组
often feels really weird and just uncalled for.
经常感觉非常奇怪且没必要
But again, note that that's what's inherited from the pure math context,
但是  这一样是从纯数学背景中继承而来的
where like we saw with the probabilities,
而就像在概率的例子中所见的
it's an incredibly natural thing to do.
这个翻转再正常不过了
And actually, I can show you one more pure math example
其实  我还可以再展示一个纯数学的例子
where even the programmers should care about this one
即使是纯程序员也应该关心此例
because it opens the doors for much faster algorithm to compute all of these.
因为它引入了一个计算卷积时快得多的算法
To set up what I mean by faster here,
为了解释我说的快得多是什么意思
let me go back and pull up some Python again
我来掏出 Python 再写点东西
and I'm going to create two different relatively big arrays.
这次我会建两个不同的长数组
each one will have 100,000 random elements in it
每个中会有 100,000 个随机元素
and I'm going to assess the run time of the convolve function from the Numpy library.
监测一下 NumPy 库中 convolve 函数的运行时间 卷积
And in this case, it runs it for multiple different iterations, tries to find an average
在这个案例中  它输出的是多次迭代中的平均用时
and it looks like on this computer, at least, it averages at 4.87 seconds.
至少在这台计算机上  看起来平均用时是 4.87 秒
By contrast, if I use a different function from the SciPy library called fftconvolve,
然而  如果我改用 SciPy 库中的 fftconvolve 函数 快速傅里叶变换卷积
which is the same just implemented differently,
它们功能一样  只是实现方法不一样
that only takes 4.3 milliseconds on average.
这次计算平均只用了 4.3 毫秒
So, three orders of magnitude improvement.
这可是 3 个数量级的优化
And again, even though it flies under a different name,
再强调一下  即使它们的名字不同
it's giving the same output that the other convolve function does,
但它和另一个卷积函数给出的输出是相同的
it's just doing something to go about it in a cleverer way.
只是用了某种更巧妙的计算方法
Remember how with the probability example,
还记得刚才那个概率论的例子吗
I said another way you could think about the convolution
我提到了另一种考虑卷积的方式
was to create this table of all the pairwise products
就是建立这个表格来计算各组合的乘积
and then add up those pairwise products along the diagonals.
然后沿着每条对角线求和
There's, of course, nothing specific to probability.
当然  这办法不只在概率论里用得上
Anytime you're convolving two different lists of numbers,
只要是要求两个数组的卷积时
you can think about it this way.
你都能这么思考
Create this kind of multiplication table with all Pairwise products
先建一个表格来计算组合乘积
and then each sum along the diagonal, corresponds to one of your final outputs.
再沿每条对角线求和  就对应着每一个输出结果
One context where this view is especially natural,
有一种情况会让这种视角显得非常自然
is when you multiply together two polynomials.
就是当将两个多项式相乘时
For example, let me take the little grid we already have
比如用这个我们已经有的网格
and replace the top terms with 1, 2x and 3x²
将上方的项替换为 1, 2x 和 3x²
and replace the other terms with 4, 5x and 6x².
将左侧的项替换为 4, 5x 和 6x²
Now, think about what it means when we're creating
然后来思考一下
all of these different pairwise products between the two lists.
这些组合的乘积意味着什么
What you're doing is essentially expanding out
其实本质上你在做一个多项式展开
the full product of the two polynomials I have written down.
即求两个多项式的全乘积
And then when you add up along the diagonal,
当你沿对角线求和
that corresponds to collecting all like terms, which is pretty neat,
其实就是在合并同类项  非常简洁优雅
expanding a polynomial and collecting like terms
扩展多项式然后合并同类项
is exactly the same process as a convolution.
其实和卷积的过程是一模一样的
But this allows us to do something that's pretty cool.
基于此我们可以做些更棒的事情
Because think about what we're saying here,
稍微回想一下我们在做的事情
we're saying if you take two different functions
我们是将两个不同的函数
and you multiply them together,
进行相乘
which is a simple point wise operation,
也就是进行一个简单的逐点运算
that's the same thing as if you had first extracted
这相当于
the coefficients from each one of those, assuming they're polynomials,
假设他们为多项式  首先提取多项式的系数
and then taking a convolution of those two lists of coefficients.
然后对这些系数组成的数组进行卷积
What makes that so interesting is that
非常有意思的是
convolutions feel, in principle, a lot more complicated than simple multiplication.
卷积看起来要比直接相乘复杂那么一点儿
And I don't just mean conceptually they are harder to think about,
我不光是说它在概念上更难理解
I mean computationally it requires more steps to perform a convolution
我的意思是相比较对两个数组进行逐点乘积来说
than it does to perform a point wise product of two different lists.
卷积需要更多的步骤来执行计算
For example, let's say I gave you two really big polynomials.
打个比方  我这有俩很长很长的多项式
Say each one with 100 different coefficients.
每个有 100 个项和相应的系数
Then if the way you multiply them was to expand out this product,
如果你通过相乘系数的办法来展开多项式
you know, filling in this entire 100×100 grid of pairwise products,
你就要填满这个 100×100 的数组乘积网格
that would require you to perform 10,000 different products.
这意味着你得先做一万次乘法运算
And then when you're collecting all the like terms along the diagonals,
然后当沿着对角线合并同类项时
that's another set of around 10,000 operations.
你得再执行大约一万次操作
More generally in the lingo, we'd say the algorithm is O(N²).
更专业一点  我们可以说这是 O(N²) 的算法
Meaning for two lists of size N,
意思是说  两个含 N 个数的数组
the way that the number of operations scales,
需要执行操作的次数
is in proportion to N².
与 N² 成正比
On the other hand,
然而
if I think of two polynomials in terms of their outputs,
如果我只考虑多项式的函数输出值
for example, sampling their values at some handful of inputs.
比如只对少数几个输入值进行采样计算
Then multiplying them only requires as many operations as the number of samples,
那么乘法运算的执行次数就等于样本数量
since again it's a pointwise operation.
因为这也是一个逐点操作
And with polynomials, you only need finitely mini samples
并且说回多项式的情况
to be able to recover the coefficients.
只需有限的样本量就足以重现系数
For example, two outputs are enough to uniquely specify a linear polynomial.
比如  两个函数输出值就能确定一个唯一的线性多项式
Three outputs would be enough to uniquely specify a quadratic polynomial
三个函数输出值就能确定一个唯一的二次多项式
and in general, if you know N distinct outputs,
而且一般来说  如果你知道 N 个函数输出值
that's enough to uniquely specify a polynomial that has N different coefficients.
就足以确定一个唯一的 N-1 次多项式
Or if you prefer, we could phrase this in the language of systems of equations.
或者我们也可以用方程组的形式来表述
Imagine I tell you, I have some polynomial
假设我有一些多项式
but I don't tell you what the coefficients are,
但是我不告诉你它们的系数是什么
those are a mystery to you.
它们对你来说是未知的
In our example, you might think of this as the product that we're trying to figure out.
在我们的例子里  你可能会认为这其实就是我们要求出的乘积
And then suppose I say,
如果假设
I'll just tell you what the outputs of this polynomial would be
我只告诉你这个多项式的输出值
if you inputted various different inputs like 0, 1, 2, 3 on and on.
假如你指定了不同的输入值如 0 1 2 3 ... 等等
And I give you enough so that you have as many equations as you have unknowns.
并且我给你提供  与未知系数的个数相同数量的方程式
It even happens to be a linear system of equations so that's nice.
简直太棒了  它甚至恰好是一个线性方程组
And in principle, at least, this should be enough to recover the coefficients.
原则上  这已经足够用来恢复系数了
So the rough algorithm outline then
所以粗略的算法大纲为
would be whenever you want to convolve two lists of numbers,
当需要对两个数组进行卷积时
you treat them like they're coefficients of two polynomials.
可以把它们视为两个多项式的系数
You sample those polynomials at enough outputs,
对这些多项式的输出值尽可能多地采样
multiply those samples pointwise,
对这些样本逐点相乘
and then solve the system to recover the coefficients
然后求解并恢复出系数
as a sneaky backdoor way to find the convolution.
这就是为卷积找了个捷径
And as I've stated it so far, at least,
目前为止  正如我所说的那样
some of you could rightfully complain, Grant, that is an idiotic plan.
有些同学可能会抱怨说  Grant  这点子可太蠢了
Because for one thing,
因为一方面
just calculating all these samples for one of the polynomials we know,
只是计算其中一个已知多项式的所有样本
already takes on the order of N² operations.
算法的时间复杂度就已经到了 O(N²) 了
Not to mention, solving that system is certainly going to be
更别说要对整个系统进行计算了
computationally as difficult as just doing the convolution in the first place.
那和一开始就做卷积没有啥区别
So like, sure, we have this connection between multiplication and convolutions
是的  在函数相乘和做卷积之间存在着联系
but all of the complexity happens in translating from one viewpoint to the other.
但是所有的复杂性都发生在视角转化的过程中
But there is a trick.
当然  这里有一个技巧
And those of you who know about fourier transforms and the FFT algorithm,
有些同学如果了解傅里叶变换和 FFT 算法的话
might see where this is going.
可能已经看懂这是咋回事了
If you're unfamiliar with these topics,
但如果你对这些话题不熟悉的话
what I'm about to say might seem completely out of the blue.
接下来要讲的东西可能会让你有点摸不着头脑
Just know that there are certain paths you could have walked in math
现在你只需要知道  存在某种数学方法
that make this more of an expected step.
一旦了解了以后  很多事情就变得顺理成章了
Basically the idea is that we have a freedom of choice here.
基本思路就是这里我们有一些自由的选择
If instead of evaluating as some arbitrary set of inputs like 0, 1, 2, 3 on and on,
如果不像原来那样  输入任意数字集合如 0 1 2 3 等等来计算
you choose to evaluate on a very specially selected set of complex numbers.
而是替换为输入特定的复数来求解
Specifically the ones that sit evenly spaced on the unit circle,
尤其是在单位圆上均匀分布的那些
what are known as the roots of unity.
所谓的单位根的话
This gives us a friendlier system.
我们就得到了一个更友好的系统
The basic idea is that
基本思路就是
by finding a number where taking its powers falls into this cycling pattern,
找到一个取幂时输出总在单位圆上循环的数就行了
it means that the system we generate
于是  我们生成的系统
is going to have a lot of redundancy in the different terms that you're calculating.
在计算的不同项中会出现很多的冗余
And by being clever about how you leverage that redundancy,
巧妙地利用这些冗余
you can save yourself a lot of work.
可以帮我们省下很多功夫
This set of outputs that I've written has a special name.
这个输出集合有一个特定名字
It's called the discrete fourier transform of the coefficients.
叫作系数的离散傅里叶变换
And if you want to learn more,
如果你想了解更多
I actually did another lecture for that same Julia MIT class,
我还在同一门 Julia MIT 课程上过另一堂课
all about discrete fourier transforms.
都是关于离散傅里叶变换的
And there's also a really excellent video on the channel Reducible,
Reducible 频道也有一期很棒的视频
talking about the fast fourier transform,
介绍了快速傅里叶变换 (FFT)
which is an algorithm for computing these more quickly.
这种算法可以让以上这些计算变得更快
Also Veritasium recently did a really good video on FFTs
真理元素最近也做了一支关于 FFT 的优质视频
so you've got lots of options.
总有一期能满足你
And that fast algorithm really is the point for us.
而这种快速算法确实是我们的重点
Again, because of all this redundancy,
再强调一下  多亏了这些冗余
there exist a method to go from the coefficients to all of these outputs
我们才能更快速地把系数  转换到这些输出点
where instead of doing on the order of N² operations,
原来需要复杂度为 O(N²) 的操作
you do on the order of N times the log(N) operations
现在只需 O(N log N)
which is much much better as you scale to big lists.
输入数组越大  这个方法的优势就越明显
And importantly, this FFT algorithm goes both ways.
更重要的是  FFT 还可以反过来用
It also lets you go from the outputs to the coefficients.
你也可以从输出对应到系数
Though bringing it all together, let's look back at our algorithm outline.
有了以上的知识  我们来回顾一下我们的算法大纲
Now, we can say, whenever you're given two long lists of numbers
只要我们有两个长数组
and you want to take their convolution,
想要计算它们的卷积的话
first, compute the fast fourier transform of each one of them,
首先分别计算它们的快速傅里叶变换
which in the back of your mind, you can just think of as treating them like
在你的脑海中  你可以把这些数看作是
they're the coefficients of a polynomial
多项式的系数
and evaluating it at a very specially selected set of points.
再将他们作为一系列具有特殊性质的点来处理
Then, multiply together the two results that you just got, point wise,
然后将两个结果逐点相乘
which is nice and fast.
这还挺容易的
And then do an inverse fast fourier transform
然后做一个快速傅里叶逆变换
and what that gives you is the sneaky back door way
我们就得到了一个计算卷积的取巧方法
to compute the convolution that we were looking for.
But this time, it only involves O(N log N) operations.
但是这回  它的复杂度仅为 O(N log N)
That's really cool to me.
太神奇了
This very specific context where convolutions show up, multiplying two polynomials,
尽管用到卷积的情景仅仅是多项式相乘
opens the doors for an algorithm
但它引出了 FFT
that's relevant everywhere else where convolutions might come up.
任何使用卷积的地方  都能看到 FFT 的身影
If you want to add probability distributions
比如  在一些大型图像处理中
to some large image processing, whatever it might be.
添加一些概率分布之类的东西
And I just think that's such a good example of why you should be excited
这有力地证明了  一个值得我们兴奋的情形在于
when you see some operation or concept in math
看似无关的几个领域  出现了相同的数学运算或概念
show up in a lot of seemingly unrelated areas.
If you want a little homework, here's something that's fun to think about.
想要课后练习的话  我留一道思考题
Explain why when you multiply two different numbers,
请解释：当你将两个不同的数字相乘时
just ordinary multiplication the way we all learn in elementary school,
就是我们在小学都学过的普通乘法那种
what you're doing is basically a convolution between the digits of those numbers.
为什么你所做的事  大体相当于求“两数各个数位”的卷积
There's some added steps with carries and the like
会用到进位之类的额外步骤
but the core step is a convolution.
不过核心步骤还是卷积
In light of the existence of a fast algorithm,
而由于这个快速算法的存在
what that means is if you have two very large integers,
这就意味着如果你要乘两个非常大的整数
then there exist a way to find their product
那么就有这么一种找到它们乘积的办法
that's faster than the method we learn in elementary school.
要比我们在小学时学的方法要快得多
That instead of requiring O(N²) operations, only requires O(N log N),
复杂度从 O(N²) 一下降到了 O(N log N)
which doesn't even feel like it should be possible.
有一种这本来没理由做得到的感觉
The catch is that before this is actually useful in practice,
要注意的是  要让这件事变得值得
your numbers would have to be absolutely monstrous.
你的两个乘数必须大得可怕
But still it's cool that such an algorithm exists.
不管怎样这种算法存在的本身就非常美妙
And next up, will turn our attention to the continuous case
下一期  我们要把目光转向连续卷积
with the special focus on probability distributions.
并且会特别讨论概率分布的情况
3Blue1Brown 中文字幕组持续招募数学、物理、计算机领域的优秀译者
欢迎有能力且有时间的译者  洽询字幕组（向 3B1B 的 B 站官号私信即可）